{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This initiative was made possible when one army was given the “Halt Order” and told to withdraw to the Canal Line at Lys. May 26 was declared a national day of prayer out of George VI’s desperation to see this initiative succeed. This initiative, codenamed Operation Dynamo, involved the use of fishing boats and civilian ships, and its end prompted Winston Churchill to give the “We shall fight on the beaches” speech. For ten points, name this “miracle” in which Allied forces were delivered from a namesake French beach in 1940.",
      "answer": [
        "evacuation from Dunkirk Dunkirk is all that is needed",
        "Operation Dynamo before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During an October 1967 protest at this facility, George Harris placed carnations in the barrels of soldiers’ guns. In 2010, Jeffrey Amos was one of two policeman shot by John Patrick Bedell at this facility’s underground Metro station. The Phoenix Project helped repair this facility after Hani Hanjour and four others hijacked American Airlines Flight 77 and crashed it into this facility. For ten points, name this Arlington County, Virginia facility that houses the Department of Defense?",
      "answer": "the Pentagon"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, one perpetrator was caught on camera wearing a shirt that said “LOL.” The victim of this event had, in 2001, fallen out with his family after using a fake passport to try to visit Disneyland Tokyo. The perpetrators of this event sprayed the nerve agent VX in the victim’s face, having been told they were filming a scene for a prank TV show. For ten points, name this February 2017 incident at an airport in Kuala Lumpur that led to tensions between Malaysia and North Korea.",
      "answer": [
        "the assassination or murder, death, etc. of Kim Jong-Nam -brother”",
        "“the assassination of Kim Jong-il’s son”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man espoused his hate for Catholics in the book Foreign Conspiracy Against the Liberties of the United States. Chemistry professor Leonard Gale helped this man perfect his most famous invention, which was boosted by Maine congressman Francis O.J. Smith’s funding for a 38-mile-long structure from Washington D.C. to Baltimore that transmitted the words “What hath God wrought” in 1844. For ten points, name this American inventor of the single-wire telegraph system.",
      "answer": "Samuel Finley Breese Morse"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s troops killed tens of thousands of Greeks by burning down Smyrna while attempting to restore lost territories during the Chanak Crisis. This man’s government rejected the Treaty of Sevres in favor of the 1923 Treaty of Lausanne. He promoted the Six Arrows ideology, which created a new modern alphabet based on Latin and banned the wearing of the fez in an attempt to westernise his newly formed republic. For ten points, name this founder of modern Turkey.",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
        "either",
        "both underlined names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A life size nude depicting a female Greek one of these people holds a small cross in a marble sculpture by Hiram Powers. Juan de Pareja was one of these people who himself became an artist after he was painted by Diego Velazquez. Two sculptures, later identified as these people rather than prisoners, were intended to flank a horned sculpture of Moses for the tomb of Pope Julius II. For ten points, name this type of person who Michelangelo showed bound to rocks as part of their forced labor.",
      "answer": "slaves"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s advance was so quick that his enemies, who had landed in Massilia, were forced to turn around after reaching the Rhone. This leader was opposed by a strategy of delay implemented by the dictator Fabius. This general, who lost to Scipio Africanus at the Battle of Zama, collected the rings of senators slain at the Battle of Cannae and marched elephants across the Alps. Rome nearly lost the Second Punic War to, for ten points, what Carthaginian general?",
      "answer": "Hannibal Barca"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Retaliation was the only ship captured by one side in this war, while the other side captured the Vengeance and Insurgent. This conflict was ended with the Treaty of Mortefontaine and triggered by Minister Talleyrand’s demand of a bribe during the XYZ Affair. George Washington was re-commissioned into the Army in preparation for, for ten points, what undeclared naval war between France and the United States during the Adams Administration?",
      "answer": "Quasi-War"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader was able to outmaneuver a group of eight regents led by Sushun to seize power and empowered the Grand Council to make most decisions. In 1898, this leader carried out a coup that ended the Hundred Days’ Reform. This leader agreed to the Self-Strengthening Movement proposed by Prince Gong, but later caused an invasion by an alliance of Western powers due to her support for the Boxer Rebellion. For ten points, name this anti-Westernizing Empress Dowager during the late Qing Dynasty.",
      "answer": "Empress Dowager Cixi or Cixi Taihou"
    },
    {
      "question": "This character’s implicit offer of marriage is declined by a man who states that he, like his prized rooks, can only fall in love once in his lifetime. The actress who plays Clara Oswald on Doctor Who also plays this character, who is remorseful after spreading rumors about the illegitimate pregnancy of Flora Hastings only to discover she has stomach cancer instead. After ascending to the throne, this woman distances herself from her mother, the Duchess of Kent, and she elects to marry the Saxon Prince Albert. Jenna Coleman portrays, for ten points, which British monarch who ruled for most of the 19th century?",
      "answer": [
        "Victoria",
        "Alexandrina Victoria"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "As chief justice, this man upheld a fine against two brothers who had tried to sell federal lottery tickets outside the District of Columbia in the case Cohens v. Virginia. This man’s legal career vaulted when he argued the losing side in the Supreme Court case of Ware v. Hylton. This man’s court held that land sales could not be voided despite the Yazoo scandal in Georgia in the case of Fletcher v. Peck. For ten points, name this Chief Justice from 1801 to 1835.",
        "answer": "John Marshall"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Marshall’s Supreme Court tenure, he firmly established this inferred power of the court, by which it could declare Congressional acts unconstitutional.",
        "answer": "judicial review do not"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One composer from this country co-wrote the Cantiones Sacrae with his mentor and collected virginal music in My Ladye Nevelles Booke after receiving a 21-year monopoly on music publishing from this country’s monarch. Another composer from this country wrote the forty-voice motet Spem in Alium and a psalm tune that Ralph [rafe] Vaughan Williams adapted into a Fantasia. For ten points, name this county in which William Byrd and Thomas Tallis composed music under Queen Elizabeth.",
        "answer": [
          "England",
          "United Kingdom",
          "Great Britain"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to his Fantasia on a Theme by Thomas Tallis, Vaughan Williams wrote a Fantasia based on this Elizabethan-era folk tune that, legend states, was written by Henry VIII for Anne Boleyn.",
        "answer": [
          "Greensleeves",
          "Fantasia on Greensleeves"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man created the National Energy Program in response to the oil shocks of the 1970s. One of his attempts at constitutional reform, the Victoria Charter, was defeated by Robert Bourassa. This man suppressed a terrorist group by invoking the War Powers Act during the October Crisis. This Prime Minister passed the Charter of Rights and Freedoms and promoted equality between French and English. For ten points, name this Liberal prime minister of Canada, a native of Quebec whose son is the current prime minister.",
        "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Trudeau’s National Energy Program proved deeply unpopular in this western province, where large oil deposits are found in the Athabasca oil sands.",
        "answer": "Alberta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An agreement reached at this meeting was nearly torpedoed when Spain did not want to return Olivenca to Portugal. Decisions made at the Council of Chaumont were ratified at this meeting, which was hampered by a crisis over who would possess Saxony or Poland. This meeting, which largely sought to restore monarchs to their pre-war thrones, was interrupted by the Hundred Days, the return of Napoleon. For ten points, name this 1814-1815 peace conference held in the capital of Austria.",
        "answer": "Congress of Vienna"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Austrian diplomat, the architect of the Carlsbad Decrees, chaired the Congress of Vienna.",
        "answer": "Klemens von Metternich"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An ancient landslide that temporarily dammed this river is known in Native American legends as the Bridge of the Gods, and occurred near its present-day Bonneville Lock and Dam. A fishing community along its Celio Falls was disrupted by the construction of a dam at The Dalles, and its longest tributary flows past Idaho Falls and Boise. The Snake River flows into, for ten points, what river that forms part of the border between Washington and Oregon?",
        "answer": "Columbia River"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other tributary of the Columbia, which flows past Salem and Eugene, drains a fertile valley that was sought by pioneers who traveled the Oregon Trail.",
        "answer": "Willamette River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was made governor of Magnesia after accusations that he had conspired with the traitor Pausanias forced him to flee his hometown. This man used the spy Sicinnus to bait an enemy fleet into fighting in the Saronic Gulf. In 483 BC, this man convinced his city to use profits from a silver strike at Laurium to build 200 triremes. The power of the Athenian navy grew immensely thanks to, for ten points, what Greek admiral who was victorious at the Battle of Salamis?",
        "answer": "Themistocles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 472 BC, Themistocles underwent this political punishment, an Athenian invention, in which the citizens of Athens voted to exile him from the city for 10 years.",
        "answer": [
          "ostracism",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite having a palsied arm, this man was never assisted in writing by his follower, John Purvey. William Courtenay condemned this man at the “Earthquake Synod.” A follower of a movement founded by this man served as the basis for the Shakespearean character of Falstaff. John Oldcastle believed in this man’s ideas, and he inspired the Czech theologian Jan Hus. For ten points, name this English thinker who attacked the excesses of the clergy as the leader of the Lollards.",
        "answer": "John Wycliffe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wycliffe translated the Bible into English; his work was based on this 4th century Latin translation of the Bible by Saint Jerome.",
        "answer": "Vulgate"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the creation of a red-light district known as the Barbary Coast. “Coyoteing” was a technique used in this event, which was first publicized by Samuel Brannan. A businessman opened a dry goods business during this event, then shifted from selling tents to selling denim pants in the 1870s. This event began after James Marshall’s discovery at Sutter’s Mill. A mass emigration of “forty-niners” took place during, for ten points, what 19th century economic “rush” on the American West Coast?",
        "answer": "California Gold Rush"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This aforementioned businessman founded his dry goods business in San Francisco in 1853, later expanding it into the jeans market.",
        "answer": "Levi Strauss do not"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Election of 1860",
      "prompt": "What...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "”Grand Old Party” first won the presidency in 1860?",
          "answer": "Republican Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Illinois politician won the election over Stephen Douglas and two others?",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the only state won by Stephen Douglas?",
          "answer": "Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "West Coast state cast its first Presidential ballots in 1860, eight years after its neighbor California?",
          "answer": "Oregon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Senator from Maine became Vice President?",
          "answer": "Hannibal Hamlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man was the Southern Democratic candidate and won the second most electoral votes?",
          "answer": "John C. Breckenridge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee politician won three border states as the Constitutional Union candidate?",
          "answer": "John Bell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man was the Constitutional Union running mate and spoke before Lincoln at the Gettysburg Address?",
          "answer": "Edward Everett"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Sweden",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Group of Norse seafarers that launched raids across Europe from bases in Sweden.",
          "answer": "Vikings"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country to the east that was dominated by Sweden until its annexation by Russia.",
          "answer": "Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country to the south that fought with Sweden over the provinces of Scania and Halland.",
          "answer": "Denmark"
        },
        {
          "question": "Institution abolished by Magnus IV of Sweden. It resulted in a largely free peasant class, but Sweden still engaged in the African form of this institution until 1813.",
          "answer": "slavery or thralls"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion of the Church of Sweden. It joined the Thirty Years’ War to help other followers of this religion in the Holy Roman Empire.",
          "answer": "Lutheranism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union that joined Sweden with other Scandinavian countries under the reign of Margaret I.",
          "answer": "Kalmar Union"
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal house that ruled Sweden with the ascension of Gustav I.",
          "answer": "House of Vasa"
        },
        {
          "question": "16th century peasant uprising that objected to heavy taxes imposed by Gustav I.",
          "answer": [
            "Dacke War",
            "anything to do with Nils Dacke"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Egypt",
      "prompt": "What...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "”Boy King’s” tomb was discovered in 1922 by Howard Carter?",
          "answer": "Tutankhamun"
        },
        {
          "question": "”Stone” features Demotic and Greek text and was used to decode hieroglyphics?",
          "answer": "Rosetta Stone"
        },
        {
          "question": "”Valley” contains many tombs of New Kingdom pharaohs?",
          "answer": "Valley of the Kings"
        },
        {
          "question": "”Jars” contained the organs of mummies?",
          "answer": "canopic jars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of Akhenaten is depicted in a bust by Thutmose?",
          "answer": "Nefertiti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rectangular tombs were the predecessors to pyramids?",
          "answer": "mastaba"
        },
        {
          "question": "Temple complex with massive statues of Ramses II was relocated to prevent it from being flooded by Lake Nasser?",
          "answer": "Abu Simbel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruler was the first to unite Upper and Lower Egypt and thus founded the First Dynasty?",
          "answer": "Menes or Narmer"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Omar Mukhtar fought for independence against this empire in the mountains of Jebel Akhdar. This European empire received Tripolitania in the Treaty of Ouchy and signed the Treaty of Wuchale to establish its colony of (20 pts)",
        "Eritrea. This empire, which made Mogadishu the capital of its Somaliland, was humiliated after its loss at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Adwa to Menelek II, but it would get its revenge over Haile Selassie. For ten points, name this European power that colonized Libya and conquered Ethiopia while ruled by Benito Mussolini."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Italy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This book names the subtitle of Mark Twain’s 19th-century European travelogue Innocents Abroad. A game based on this book is played by the March sisters in the first chapter of Little Women. A re-imagining of this book by (20 pts)",
        "Nathaniel Hawthorne concerns a railway trip made by Mr. Smooth-it-away and is titled “The Celestial Railroad.” William (10 pts)",
        "Thackeray used a city that appears in this book to title his novel Vanity Fair. For ten points, name this allegory about Christian’s journey to the Celestial City, written by John Bunyan."
      ],
      "answer": "The Pilgrim’s Progress from This World to That Which Is To Come"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During a meeting with Melih Absel, this man said “The illegal we do immediately. The unconstitutional takes a little longer.” This man outlined one of his famous strategies in his book The Necessity for Choice; that strategy was a response to an earlier policy of (20 pts)",
        "“massive retaliation” and involved a “flexible response” to nuclear threats. This man’s frequent flying between Middle Eastern capitals, attempting to resolve the (10 pts)",
        "Yom Kippur War, became known as “shuttle diplomacy.” For ten points, name this proponent of d´etente who served as Secretary of State under Presidents Ford and Nixon."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry Alfred Kissinger or Heinz Alfred Kissinger"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was once taken over by the Small Swords Society. An incident within this city, in which Isao Oyama shot an airport guard to death, helped heighten tensions prior to (20 pts)",
        "World War II. An international settlement was built in this city after it became the highest profile port to be opened to trade in the Treaty of Whampoa. Most of Jiang Qing’s (10 pts)",
        "Gang of Four was based in this city, which is now the site of the international Bund, or Waitan, district. For ten points, name this port city of eastern China, one of the most populous cities in the world."
      ],
      "answer": "Shanghai"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thermal voltage is used in a set of three equations describing different currents flowing through these devices in the Ebers-Moll model. Walter Brattain, William Shockley, and John Bardeen (20 pts)",
        "invented these devices at Bell Labs and accordingly won the 1956 Nobel in Physics. The MOSFET variety of these devices is now more popular than their bipolar junction type. Moore’s law states that the number of these devices per square inch on an integrated (10 pts)",
        "circuit doubles about every two years. For ten points, name these semiconducting devices that amplify electronic signals and were used in a type of namesake radio."
      ],
      "answer": "transistors"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A resident of this city, Benjamin Bache, published the Aurora newspaper here. A resident of this city was social reformer and physician Benjamin (20 pts)",
        "Rush. Thousands of slaves fleeing the Haitian Revolution settled in this city in 1793, leading to a deadly outbreak of yellow fever that summer. At a meeting in this city, the (10 pts)",
        "Connecticut Compromise settled a dispute over proportional representation between the Virginia and New Jersey plans. For ten points, what city hosted the Constitutional Convention?"
      ],
      "answer": "Philadelphia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The three-stratum and CHC theories were formulated in the late 20th-century to explain this concept. This trait’s “crystallized” form typically increases with age, while its “fluid” form tends to decrease. Raven’s Progressive Matrices and the (20 pts)",
        "Wason four-card test are used to evaluate this trait, which was first studied in a psychological sense by Alfred (10 pts)",
        "Binet [bin-ay] in 1905. The Flynn effect quantifies the general rise of this quantity in society over time. For ten points, name this concept, the ability to process information and solve problems, often measured and reported via a “quotient” after taking a test."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "intelligence",
        "IQ",
        "intelligence quotient"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event included an agreement on the internationalization of the port of Dalian. Southern Sakhalin and the Kuril Islands were promised to one country at this event. This meeting, which convened in the (20 pts)",
        "Livadia Palace, established forced labor as a means of reparations and agreed on a desire for the total unconditional (10 pts)",
        "surrender of Germany. For ten points, name this 1945 conference, held five months prior to the Potsdam Conference, at which Stalin, Churchill, and Roosevelt discussed post-war Europe."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yalta Conference",
        "Crimean Conference",
        "Argonaut Conference"
      ]
    }
  ]
}